## Curriculum Vitae

# NOAH EVERETT

November 28, 2023

## Table of Contents

### ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

| Research Summary                      | NoahEverett898@gmail.com ➤              |
|---------------------------------------|---|
| ·                                     | 9                                       |
| Education                             | $(507) \ 215-3209 \ $                   |
| Research Appointments                 |   |
| Honors and Awards                     | https://linkedin.com/in/Noah-Everett in |
| Scientific Collaborations3            | https://github.com/Noah-Everett 🖸       |
| Professional Service and Leadership 3 | https://Noah-Everett.github.io          |
| Research References                   |   |
| Research Projects                     |   |
| Presentations and Publications        |   |
|                                       |   |

### RESEARCH SUMMARY

As an undergraduate, I have done research in theoretical and experimental particle physics and optical physics, pure mathematics, and machine learning at South Dakota Mines, SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory, and Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory. I have been fortunate to work with truly amazing people and either directly or indirectly with experiments such as ANNIE, LUX-ZEPLIN, nEXO, SciBooNE, and SuperCDMS.

#### **EDUCATION**

2020-2024

South Dakota Mines (South Dakota School of Mines and Technology)

B.S. Physics and Mathematics

Minors: Computer Science and Computational Statistics

GPA: 3.93/4.00

#### Research Appointments

(Additional information on individual projects can be found in the Research Projects Section and is hyperlinked by each project)

Aug 2023-Present

Undergraduate Research Assistant, South Dakota Mines *PI:* Dr. Randy Hoover, Computer Science Department *Contributions:* 

• Investigating the use of convolutional deep learning methods for temporal graph forecasting (additional information)

Jun 2023-Aug 2023

DOE SULI Intern, Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory PI: Dr. Patrick Fox, Theory Department Contributions:

- Investigated the feasibility of using SciBooNE to search for dark photons through visible decay channels (additional information)
- Attended the International Symposium on Lattice Field Theory (Lattice 2023) and the 14<sup>th</sup> International Neutrino Summer School 2023

Noah Everett 1 Curriculum Vitae

Aug 2022-Present

Undergraduate Research Assistant, South Dakota Mines *PI:* Dr. Patrick Fleming, Mathematics Department *Contributions:* 

- Found isomorphisms that map between the extended  $\mathbb{R}^2$  plane, (hemi)sphere, and  $\mathbb{R}^3$  vector space constructions of the real projective plane (additional information)
- Presented findings at Mathematical Association of America (MAA) Rocky Mountain Section 2023 meeting and a math department colloquium

Jun 2022–Aug 2022

DOE SULI Intern, SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory *PI:* Dr. Brian Mong, Fundamental Physics Directorate *Contributions:* 

- Created a Monte Carlo simulation of electrostatic chamber radon assay systems
- Developed an analysis method to determine the initial populations of long-lived radioactive isotopes in assayed materials with complete decay history fitting (additional information)
- Helped assemble a new electrostatic chamber radon assay system
- Presented results at the Stanford Physics, Identity, and Equity Workshop (SPIEW) and the American Physical Society (APS) Prairie Section 2022 meeting

Dec 2021-Present

Undergraduate Research Assistant, South Dakota Mines *PI*: Dr. Jingbo Wang, Physics Department *Contributions*:

- Developing a new likelihood-based reconstruction method for AN-NIE (additional information)
- Conducting a simulation-based feasibility study for a neutrino-argon measurement in ANNIE (additional information)
- Restored ANNIE's simulation softwares including GENIE, WCSim (GEANT4-based detector simulation), and ANNIEDirt (GEANT4-based fast particle propagator) after their ~5 year hiatus
- Miscellaneous work on ANNIE software including creating Docker images, bash scripts, documentation, and maintaining and contributing to ANNIE's simulation and analysis softwares
- Presented results at the 2023 APS April meeting and multiple student research symposia and ANNIE collaboration meetings

Jan 2021-Dec 2021

Undergraduate Research Assistant, South Dakota Mines *PI*: Dr. Richard Schnee, Physics Department *Contributions*:

- Developed an environmental monitoring system for the ultra-low radon cleanroom at South Dakota Mines (additional information)
- Assisted with material assays for SuperCDMS and LUX-ZEPLIN
- Assisted in assembling the cleanroom tent for a new cold emanation system and started the commissioning of the system

Noah Everett 2 Curriculum Vitae

## Honors and Awards

| Aug 2023  | Member of the ANNIE Collaboration  Context: First and only undergraduate collaboration member  |
|-----------|--|
| Apr 2023  | APS Division of Particles and Fields Travel Grant for April Meeting Context: Gave a talk in the Neutrinos IV (non-undergraduate) session   |
| Mar 2023  | Outstanding Physics Junior, South Dakota Mines  Context: Awarded to 1-2 physics juniors chosen by the physics department faculty each year   |
| Mar 2023  | Leadership Award for The Society of Physics Students (SPS), South Dakota Board of Regents  |
| Nov 2022  | Private Dinner with Dr. Nigel Lockyer and Gov. Mike Rounds  Context: I was 1 of 2 students (and the only undergraduate) that attended a private dinner with Dr. Nigel Lockyer (former director of Fermilab and TRIUMF), Gov. Mike Rounds (former Governor and current Senator of South Dakota), and other prominent community members. Students were invited by the physics associate department head. |
| Apr 2022  | Sigma Pi Sigma Honor Society   |
| 2020-2023 | Dean's List (all semesters)  |

### SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATIONS

2023-Present

Accelerator Neutrino Neutron Interaction Experiment (ANNIE)

Member: ANNIE is a 26-ton gadolinium-doped water Cherenkov detector on the Booster Neutrino Beam (BNB) at Fermilab. The primary physics goal of ANNIE is to make precision measurements of the number of final state neutrons from neutrino interactions in water to improve the systematic uncertainties of next-generation long-baseline neutrino experiments. In addition, ANNIE is also doing detector R&D on new Large Area Picosecond PhotoDetectors (LAPPDs) and Water-based Liquid Scintillator (WbLS) detector medium. The ANNIE collaboration consists of more than 40 collaborators from 19 institutions and 2 national labs in 5 countries.

## PROFESSIONAL SERVICE AND LEADERSHIP

May 2023–Present

Physics Departmental Action Team

Member: Implement change to support department improvement. This consists of diversity, equity, and inclusion efforts, implementation of active learning, and other departmental issues. I am 1 of 3 undergraduate members selected by the physics department to be on the team.

Oct 2023–Present

APS Inclusion, Diversity, and Equity Alliance (APS-IDEA)

Member: The APS Inclusion, Diversity, and Equity Alliance (APS-IDEA) is an APS Innovation Fund initiative with a mission of empowering the physics community to enact strategies for improving equity, diversity, and inclusion.

Noah Everett 3 Curriculum Vitae

Apr 2023-Present

Society of Physics Students (SPS) and Sigma Pi Sigma (National Council) Associate Zone Councilor (AZC): I am AZC for Zone 11 (which spans MN, SD, ND, NE, and IA). I was elected to this position as a result of a Zone wide election. I manage correspondence between the SPS national branch and chapters in Zone 11, along with events and outreach activities across Zone 11.

Co-Chair of the Burnout Committee: The burnout committee is tasked with discussing and implementing aid at a national level for students experiencing burnout which, according to a 2022 poll, was one of the most important issues facing physics students.

Apr 2022–Aug 2023

South Dakota Mines' Society of Physics Students (SPS) Chapter

Vice President: Generally support the chapter by finding outreach events, club activities, assist in management, and lead meetings.

Feb 2022-Present

Health and Fitness Club

Founder, President (Feb 2022–Apr 2023), and Vice President (Apr 2023–Present): The Health and Fitness Club is a student community focused on promoting physical and mental well-being through activities, advice, and support in various areas of health and fitness. To this end, I founded and was the club president until April 2023 when I stepped down as president to support the next generation of leadership.

Apr 2022-Present

Peer Mentor

Physics and Mathematics Peer Mentor: I serve as a peer mentor in the First Year Peer Mentoring Program at South Dakota Mines, guiding first-year students in acclimating to campus life, offering academic support, and fostering a sense of community through workshops and events.

## RESEARCH REFERENCES

| Jingbo Wang,<br>Ph.D     | Assistant Professor of Physics, South Dakota Mines<br>Research Supervisor and Course Instructor<br>Jingbo.Wang@sdsmt.edu    (605) 394-5206   |
|--------------------------|--|
| Patrick Fox,<br>Ph.D     | Senior Scientist and Deputy Head, Theory Division, Fermilab Research Supervisor PJFox@fnal.gov $\parallel$ (831) 359-7998  |
| Brian Mong,<br>Ph.D      | Associate Scientist, SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory Research Supervisor bung@slac.stanford.edu    (650) 926-5540   |
| Patrick Fleming,<br>Ph.D | Assistant Professor of Mathematics, South Dakota Mines<br>Supervisor and Course Instructor<br>Patrick.Fleming@sdsmt.edu    (605) 394-2471  |
| Richard Schnee,<br>Ph.D  | Professor and Head, Physics Department, South Dakota Mines<br>Member of the Particle Physics Projects Prioritization Panel (P5)<br>Research Supervisor<br>Richard.Schnee@sdsmt.edu    (605) 394-5206 |

Noah Everett 4 Curriculum Vitae

## RESEARCH PROJECTS

(This section contains information about each of my research projects as opposed to research appointments as in the Research Appointments Section. Additional information about each project can be found at Noah-Everett.github.io/Research.)

#### Aug 2023-Present

Using Convolutional Deep Learning Methods for Temporal Graph Forecasting

Advisor: Randy Hoover, South Dakota Mines, Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Department

Contributions:

- Implementing the proposed model with PyTorch Geometric
- Evaluating the model's performance with multiple temporal graph datasets

Jun 2023–Present

Feasibility Study for Using Direction Sensitive Photosenors for Detailed Track Reconstruction in Unsegmented Scintillation Detectors

Advisor: None (Independent Project)

Contributions:

- Created a fully configurable detector simulation using Geant4 and NEST to predict detector performance
- Created an analytical ray tracer for geometric lenses to design a preliminary lens system for the detector's direction sensitive photosensors
- Developing traditional (likelihood-based) and deep learning event reconstruction methods to determine the optimal detector configurations along with the efficacy of the general detector design

Jun 2023–Aug 2023

Search for Dark Photon Decay Via  $A' \to \ell^+ \ell^-$  in SciBooNE and ANNIE Advisor: Patrick Fox, Fermilab, Theory Department Contributions:

- Calculated the expected number of events in SciBooNE's SciBar and ANNIE's water tank as a function of the kinetic mixing strength and mass
- Proposed reconstruction methods to tag dark photon decays in Sci-BooNE and ANNIE

May 2023–Aug 2023

Analytical Meridional, Non-Paraxial Ray Tracing

Advisor: None (Independent Project)

Contributions:

- Presented a method for meridional (2-dimensional), non-paraxial (non-small angle approximation) ray tracing
- Provided a Python simulation framework for sensitivity analysis of optical systems, reward function for reinforcement-based lens design, etc.

Aug 2022–Present

Likelihood-based Track Reconstruction for ANNIE Advisor: Jingbo Wang, South Dakota Mines, Physics Department Contributions:

- Developed a Geant4 simulation to produce data needed to predict detector response, including photon emission, stopping power (dE/dx), and photon transmission distance
- Developing charged lepton PMT and LAPPD detector response prediction, the first of its kind for LAPPDs

Noah Everett 5 Curriculum Vitae

Aug 2022-Present

Isomorphisms for Real Projective Plane Constructions

Advisor: Patrick Fleming, South Dakota Mines, Mathematics Department Contributions:

- Found isomorphisms that map between the extended  $\mathbb{R}^2$  plane, (hemi)sphere, and  $\mathbb{R}^3$  vector space projective plane constructions
- Investigated the similarity of projective plane constructions to an idealized type of photosensor

Jun 2022–Aug 2022

Improving Radon Assay Data Analysis With Complete Decay History Fitting

Advisor: Brian Mong, SLAC Fundamental Physics Directorate Contributions:

- Created a Monte Carlo simulation of electrostatic chamber radon assay systems
- Developed an analysis method to determine the initial populations of long-lived radioactive isotopes in assayed materials
- Helped assemble a new electrostatic chamber radon assay system

Dec 2021-Present

Feasibility Study For Neutrino-Argon Interaction Measurement in ANNIE Advisor: Jingbo Wang, South Dakota Mines, Physics Department Contributions:

- Restored ANNIE's simulation softwares including GENIE, WCSim (GEANT4-based detector simulation), and ANNIEDirt (GEANT4-based fast particle propagator) after their ~5 year hiatus
- ANNIE software work including creating Docker images, bash scripts, documentation, and maintaining and contributing to ANNIE's simulation and analysis softwares
- Modified ANNIE's simulation softwares to accurately simulate proposed detector modifications
- Produced the entirety of the simulation results used for the study

Jan 2021-Dec 2021

Environmental Monitoring System for Cleanrooms *Advisor:* Richard Schnee, South Dakota Mines, Physics Department *Contributions:* 

- Developed an environmental monitoring system for the ultra-low radon cleanroom at South Dakota Mines (illustration here)
- Assisted with material assays for SuperCDMS and LUX-ZEPLIN
- Assisted in assembling the cleanroom tent for the new cold emanation system and started the commissioning of the system

Noah Everett 6 Curriculum Vitae

## PRESENTATIONS AND PUBLICATIONS

(Oral and Poster Presentations; Papers and Unpublished Notes)

## **PAPERS**

- 1. ANNIE Collaboration, "Analysis Techniques for the Accelerator Neutrino Neutron Interaction Experiment," Dec 2023
- 2. Everett, N., Wang, J., Gardiner, S., et al., "Feasibility Study of Neutrino-Argon Measurement in ANNIE," Dec 2023 (draft upon request)
- 3. Everett, N., "Using Direction Sensitive Photosensors for Detailed Topological Reconstruction in Unsegmented Scintillation Detectors Without Drift Field," Dec 2023 (draft upon request)
- 4. **Everett, N.**, Fleming, P., "On Real Projective Plane Constructions and Their Isomorphisms," 2023 Nov 27
- 5. Everett, N., "Analytical Meridional, Non-Paraxial Ray Tracing," 2023 Oct 15
- 6. **Everett, N.**, P. Fox, "Illuminating Excluded Dark Photon Parameter Space With Sci-BooNE," 2023 Aug 11

### ORAL PRESENTATIONS

- Oct 2023 Wang, J., **Everett, N.**, "ANNIE Phase 3: Possible Argon Target Deployment," ANNIE Collaboration Meeting, Batavia, IL
- Apr 2023 **Everett, N.**, "Finding Projective Plane Isomorphisms And Exploring Their Applications in Particle Physics Detectors," George F. Duck Math Colloquium, Rapid City, SD
- Apr 2023 **Everett, N.**, "Finding Projective Plane Isomorphisms And Exploring Their Applications in Particle Physics Detectors," MAA Rocky Mountain Section Meeting, Spearfish, SD
- Apr 2023 **Everett, N.**, "Likelihood-Based Reconstruction Techniques in ANNIE," APS April Meeting, Neutrinos IV, Minneapolis, MN
- Apr 2023 **Everett, N.**, "Likelihood-Based Reconstruction Techniques in ANNIE," South Dakota Mines' Student Research Symposium, Rapid City, SD
- Feb 2023 **Everett, N.**, "Detector Response Prediction and Likelihood-Based Charged Lepton Reconstruction," ANNIE Collaboration Meeting, Batavia, IL
- Feb 2023 Wang, J., **Everett, N.**, "Possibility of Measuring Neutrons from Neutrino-Argon Interactions in ANNIE," ANNIE Collaboration Meeting, Batavia, IL
- Dec 2022 **Everett, N.**, "Finding Projective Plane Isomorphisms and Exploring Their Applications in Particle Physics Detectors," Fall 2022 Math Research Symposium, Rapid City, SD
- Dec 2022 **Everett, N.**, "Likelihood Based Secondary Lepton Reconstruction for ANNIE," Fall 2022 Physics Experimental Design Research Symposium, Rapid City, SD
- Aug 2022 **Everett, N.**, "Radon Assay for nEXO," SLAC SULI Presentation Seminar, Menlo Park, CA

Noah Everett 7 Curriculum Vitae

### POSTER PRESENTATIONS

- Aug 2023 Everett, N., Fox, P., "Search For Dark Photons Via A' → ℓ<sup>+</sup>ℓ<sup>-</sup> in SciBooNE and ANNIE," 2023 Fermilab SULI Poster Session, Batavia, IL
   Oct 2022 Everett, N., Mong, B., "Improving Radon Assays for Ultra Sensitive Experiments."
- Oct 2022 **Everett, N.**, Mong, B., "Improving Radon Assays for Ultra Sensitive Experiments," 2022 APS Prairie Section Meeting, Sioux Falls, SD
- Oct 2022 **Everett, N.**, Wang, J., "Feasibility Study of  $\nu$ -Ar Interaction Measurement in ANNIE," 2022 Physics Congress, Washington, DC
- Jul 2022 **Everett, N.**, Mong, B., "Radon Emanation for nEXO," Stanford Physics, Identity, and Equity Workshop (SPIEW), Stanford, CA
- Apr 2022 **Everett, N.**, Wang, J., "Feasibility Study For Neutrino-Argon Interaction Measurement in ANNIE," South Dakota Mines' Student Research Symposium, Rapid City, SD

## Unpublished Notes

- 1. Everett N., "Likelihood-Based Charged Lepton Reconstruction for ANNIE," 2023 Jan 20
- 2. **Everett N.**, "Improving Radon Assay Data Analysis With Complete Decay History Fitting," 2022 Aug 26

Noah Everett 8 Curriculum Vitae